Last modified: 2010 Nov 13

pyTrix

License: MIT, unless otherwise specified in the source file.

I started pyTrix (TM) on in August 2004 as a place for economists and other to store statistically and econometrically oriented Python utilities. It is now part of a larger EconPy (TM) project, which will include contributions in agent-based simulation. In addition, a better place to get most of the stats funtionality (and more) is the statsmodel scikit for SciPy. Please contribute to this archive by send packages, modules, or links to:
aisaac AT american.edu

Browse the code. Or see the documentation for a description of the code archive: online.

This rest of this page is an idiosyncratic sampling of some Python resources for social scientists. If you are unaware of the computational potential of Python, you can find a brief introduction on my Software for Economists page.

As free and open source software, Python supports Claerbout's notion of really reproducible research. (More references.)

An article about computational science in a scientific publication is not the scholarship itself, it is merely advertising of the scholarship. The actual scholarship is the complete software development environment and the complete set of instructions which generated the figures.
Buckheit and Donoho

IronPython is an open-source implementation of Python that is integrated with the .NET Framework. ironclad allows IronPython users to import and use compiled CPython extensions.

Comments on parrallel Python:
If you want to do computations in parallel, there are at least three alternatives.
IPython1 is an enhanced Python interactive shell that supports distributed interactive computing.
The other two require you to link to MPI. You can run a modified Python linked with mpi, or you can use regular Python and a module linked with mpi. You then run your application using mpirun, just as with a C/C++ based parallel program.
There exist several python mpi wrappers: mpi4py (which gets rave reviews in combination with Open MPI), pypar, PyMPI. If you are using NumPy, note that note all implementations can communicate efficiently with NumPy arrays (using the low-level C API to pass pointers to arrays).

Theano "is a Python library that allows you to define, optimize, and evaluate mathematical expressions involving multi-dimensional arrays efficiently." Make easy use of your GPU for computation!

Python IDEs

There are many Python IDEs, but the most commonly used is IDLE, which is included in standard Python installations.

Spyder is a very interesting alternative. "Spyder (Scientific PYthon Development EnviRonment) is a free open-source Python development environment providing MATLAB-like features in a simple and light-weighted software."

DreamPie tries to improve on IDLE by better supporting TKinter GUIs.

Dr. Python gets some good reviews. (License: GPL)

GUI

PyQt “is a set of Python bindings for Nokia's Qt application framework”. (License: GPL) It is an extensive library with a good reputation. Similar functionality is provided by the newer PySide, under a more liberal license. (License: LGPL)

Econometric and Other Utilities for Python

pygsl "provides a Python interface for the GNU scientific library (gsl)".

The IO module is a collection input-output utilities. These are intended to supplement those in SciPy, or sometimes to provide "light weight" alternatives, not to provide a full set of services.

pyGAUSS is a collection of GAUSS command "look alikes" for use with SciPy/numpy.

unitroot is a collection of unitroot tests for use with SciPy/numpy. Since you can access R via Python, these Unit root and cointegration tests for time series data may also be of interest.

tseries is a collection of time-seris related objects for use with SciPy/numpy. Graphing functionality requires Matplotlib.

pytrix is a collection econometric and other utilities for use with SciPy/numpy. This is mostly stuff "harvested" from other websites.

QME-DEV Workbench "is a data analysis workbench based on Python, SciPy, Numpy and MatPlotLib(PyLab) and uses wxPython for the GUI."

probstat is a collection of probability and statistics routines for Python (written in C). BioPython includes a Logistic Regression implementation. The Muac distribution includes Python code for computing the 2-dimensional KS (Kolmogorov-Smirnov) test for two samples. (Archived: ks2.py.)

PAIDA is pure Python and implements the AIDA abstract interface for data analysis.

StatPy is "a collection of resources to help you do statistical computing with Python".

Linear Programming: lp_solve "is a Mixed Integer Linear Programming (MILP) solver" with a Python wrapper. (License: LGPL) PuLP "provides a nice syntax for the creation of linear problems, and a simple way to call the solvers to perform the optimization." (License: BSD)

PyAMG "is a library of Algebraic Multigrid (AMG) solvers with a convenient Python interface". For solving very large linear systems.

PyRoot provides Python bindings for the impressive Root C++ library for data analysis.

Jonathan Taylor offers a numpy/scipy package for some linear statistical models.

The oddly named TextModeller implements maximum entropy estimation for large sample spaces. (The name is explained by the applications in the website tutorial.)

mpfit does "Levenberg-Marquardt least-squares minimization, based on MINPACK-1". SciPy also offers minimizers, including constrained minimizers like fmin_cobyla, which you can use with the loss function of your choice.

clnum does rational and arbitrary precision floating point arithmetic.

VFGEN can for generate Python code to be used with the SciPy ODEINT function.

PyMat is a Python interface to MatLab.

Gary Strangman's stats.py (which needs his pstat.py list manipulation module). The stats.py module in SciPy is a modification of the Strangman module, which is more useful if you are using numpy.

Stefan Mueller-Stach's Python Math Lab contains potentially useful utilities.

Bryn Keller's datastruct.py has useful, lightweight utilities.
(License: LGPL)

PyKF provides basic Kalman filtering.

Mocapy "is a Dynamic Bayesian Network toolkit, implemented in Python. It supports discrete, Gaussian, Dirichlet, Kent and Von Mises-Fisher nodes. Inference and learning is done by Gibbs sampling/Monte Carlo-EM (which can be done on a cluster computer)".

Python Bayes Network Toolkit "supports static Bayesian Networks with discrete variables."

Mark Hoemmen's Sparse Matrix Converter.
(License: BSD.)

Pyvox is image processing for neuropsychiatrists, but others may find the code useful as well.

The Modular toolkit for Data Processing (MDP) is a Python library to implement data processing elements (nodes) and to combine them into data processing sequences (flows). Includes Principal Components analysis in its implemented algorithms. Use MDP together with Symeig, which wraps useful LAPACK eigenvalue functions. Includes "Principal Component Analysis (PCA), Independent Component Analysis (ICA), Slow Feature Analysis (SFA), Growing Neural Gas (GNG), Factor Analysis, Fisher Discriminant Analysis (FDA), and Gaussian Classifiers".

Ryan Krauss's control systems toolkit "is for analyzing linear, time-invariant dynamic systems and feedback control systems using the Laplace transform." (License: BSD)

Wavelets: Scipy offers a modest wavelet library. There is also a separate PyWavelets module.

buildgrid is a Python extension module (in C) to build regular grids from scattered 2D data.

CGAL-Python is implemented using Boost.Python to provide Python access to the Computational Geometry Algorithms Library (a C++ library of geometric algorithms).

OT: I'm hoping someone will translate Andy Warne's SVAR Matlab code to numpy very soon.

PyDX "is a package for working with calculus (differential geometry), arbitrary precision arithmetic (using gmpy), and interval arithmetic." (GPL) (Be sure to consider the dependencies.) It also does automatic differentiation.

PYADOLC provides Python bindings to ADOLC. Great for automatic differentiation.

SalStat is a Python based SPSS-like statistical analysis package.

Optimization

The SciPy optimization modules.
OpenOpt provides a unified interface to a variety of solvers. (License: BSD; Language: Python)
nlpy can read optimization problems coded in the AMPL modeling language (and by implication problems coded in MathProg).
ffnet implements feed-forward neural networks.
petsc4py provides Python bindings for the Portable, Extensible Toolkit for Scientific Computation (PETSc). (License: BSD; PETSc License: mostly public domain but a little GPL) PETSc is "a suite of data structures and routines for the scalable (parallel) solution of scientific applications modeled by partial differential equations".
FiPy is a finite-volume partial differential equation (PDE) solver, written in Python.
PySUNDIALS allows Python access to the SUNDIALS (SUite of Nonlinear and DIfferential/ALgebraic equation Solvers)
David Cournapeau's module for Expectation Maximization for Gaussian Mixture Models.
Python Equations fit themselves to 2D and 3D data sets.
pymc "is a python module that implements the Metropolis-Hastings algorithm as a python class, and is extremely flexible and applicable to a large suite of problems."

Parallelization

Jug is a pure Python "Task-Based Parallelization Framework".

Simulation

PyDSTools "is an integrated simulation, modeling and analysis package for dynamical systems". (License: BSD.) Depends on SciPy.

SFE "is a finite element solver used so far for simulations in (bio)mechanics and shape optimization of closed channels w.r.t. fluid flow." (License: GPL)

SimPy supports "object-oriented, process-based discrete-event simulation".
License: GNU Lesser GPL (LGPL)

GarlicSim "is a platform for writing, running and analyzing simulations".

PySCeS: The Python Simulator for Cellular Systems. (License: GPL) Hint: for larger systems, increase the parameter mxstep in the odeint function call from its default of 500 to a higher value (such as 1000 or 3000).

Data Exchange

PyTables " is a package for managing hierarchical datasets ... built on top of the HDF5 library". (License: BSD; Language: Python)

pysclint provides interfaces to major scientific libraries, like HDF, netCDF and MPI. pupynere is a "PUre PYthon NEtcdf REader". (Language: Python; License: MIT) You can also read and write netCDF files with netcdf4-python.

PyNIO "is a Python package that allows read and/or write access to a variety of data formats using an interface modelled on netCDF." (License: University of Illinois/NCSA Open Source License)

netcdf4-python is a Python interface to netCDF data.

Graphics and Graphics Related Applications

PyXL creates three-dimensional Voronoi tesselations. Relies on the Qhull package. PyXL generates 3D graphical representations for use with the VTK package.

PyCuda "lets you access Nvidia‘s CUDA parallel computation API from Python". (License: MIT/X Consortium license)

PyObjC provides a "bridge" between Python and Objective-C, allowing you to write "Cocoa GUI applications on Mac OS X in pure Python".

Image Processing

OpenCV now supports the NumPy array interface.

Graphs (Directed and Undirected)

python-graph implements a number of standard graph algorithms.

You may wish to examine one effort to produce a standard Python Graph API. Includes a proposal for GraphABC (an abstract base class for graphs).

NetworkX is suitable for "the creation, manipulation, and study of the structure, dynamics, and functions of complex networks." You can alternatively use igraph, which has a Python wrapper. (License: GPL)

Graphics Animation Toolkit (Gato)

peak-o-mat "is a curve fitting program aimed for fast and easy fitting of spectroscopic data, especially if you face a large amount of similar spectra."

Feed Forward Neural Nets

NIPY is a collection of neuro-imaging tools for Python. (License under discussion, but currently GPL)

Odds and Ends

BMELibPy_ is a parital translation of the BMElib MATLAB library.
Still uses Numeric.
The variogram methods are complete.
.. _BMELibPy: http://bmelibpy.sourceforge.net


Shapely_ "is a thin wrapper for libgeos_c".
Allows working with 2D geospatial geometries.
Based on GEOS. (License: BSD)

.. _Shapley: http://pypi.python.org/pypi/Shapely


`sftp_client`_ is a simple SSH2 `FTP client`_.

.. _sftp_client: sftp_client.py
.. _`FTP client`: http://www.american.edu/econ/notes/soft.htm#ftp



Easily pass numpy arrays to MATLAB with mlabwrap_.

.. _mlabwrap: http://mlabwrap.sourceforge.net/

FiPy "is an object oriented, partial differential equation (PDE) solver". Documentation is very good. (License: public domain.) Also see OOF. (License: public domain.)

PyFFmpeg wraps the FFmpeg library, allowing audio-visual manipulations via a simple Python interface.
samplerate is a python wrapper around the Sampling Rate Conversion (SRC) library of Erik Castrop de Lopo. It provides "a python package to convert sampling rate of audio signals ... using sinc interpolation and polyphase implementation". PyAudioLab reads and writes audio files as numpy arrays. Requires libsndfile, (a cross-platform C library for reading and writing files containing sampled sound). (License: LGPL) There is documentation. Currently no IO capabilities.
PyAudiere provides a "high-level audio interface for Python". Depends on the Audiere sound library. (License: LGPL)
PyAudio if Python bindings for PortAudio. Offers (blocking-mode only) support for IO. (License: MIT)
pyPortAudio is a "Python interface to the PortAudio multiplatform audio I/O library". Requires libsndfile.
fastaudio.tar.gz is recommended as an alternative to pyPortAudio (features non-blocking calls, plus far greater stability). Requires Pyrex to build from source, but there's a pre-built windows binary.
PySndObj is SWIG based. Looks promising.

Mac users will want a more up-to-date Python. Try universal python.

The Golly game-of-life simulator is written in C++ but is scriptable in Python.

PyVISA "enables you to control all kinds of measurement equipment through various busses (GPIB, RS232, USB) with Python programs."

Windows users can add command and control speech recognition.

spawn external commands on Windows platforms.

PyCluster clustering algorithms, including k-means.

Extensibility

PyBindGen generates Python bindings for C/C++ libraries.

Little Tricks

Start by reading Python pitfalls.

A simple way to reverse a sequence: seq[::-1].

A fast way to get an element from a set (or other iterable): for x in myset: break.

Here is a way to understand numpy.dot: the operation uses the last dimension of the first argument and the next-to-last dimension of the second argument. When given two 1-D arrays, dot() essentially computes the inner product. When given two 2-D arrays, dot() essentially computes matrix multiplication.